I think the future of this planet depends on humans,
أنا أعتقد ان مستقبل هذا الكوكب يعتمد على البشر،
not technology, and we already have the knowledge --
وليس التكنولوجيا، ونحن نملك المعرفة بالفعل.
we’re kind of at the endgame with knowledge.
نحن تقريبا في المباراة الفاصلة مع المعرفة،
But we’re nowhere near the endgame
لكننا لسنا قرب نهاية اللعبة
when it comes to our perception.
عندما يتعلق الأمر بتصورنا.
We still have one foot in the dark ages.
لا زال لدينا قدم في العصور المظلمة.
And when you listen to some of the presentations here --
وعندما تستمع لبعض المحاضرات هنا
and the extraordinary range of human capability, our understandings --
ومدى المقدرة الخارقة للبشر، فهمنا،
and then you contrast it with the fact
ومن ثم تقارنها بالواقع
we still call this planet, "Earth:" it’s pretty extraordinary --
لا زلنا نسمي هذا الكوكب، "الأرض". انه غير عادي بشدة.
we have one foot in the dark ages.
لدينا قدم واحدة في العصور المظلمة.
Just quickly: Aristotle, his thing was, "It’s not flat, stupid, it’s round."
بسرعة، أرسطو، حجته كانت، انها ليست مسطحة، غباء، انها مدورة.
Galileo -- he had the Inquisition, so he had to be a little bit more polite --
غاليليو، تم إخضاعه لمحاكم التفتيش حتى يؤدب قليلاً.
his was, "It’s not in the middle, you know."
لقد كان، انه ليس في الوسط، أنتم تعرفون.
And Hawkes: "it’s not earth, stupid, it’s ocean."
و هوكس: انها ليست الأرض، غباء، انها المحيط.
This is an ocean planet.
هذا كوكب المحيط.
T.S. Eliot really said it for me --
قالها تي.اس. اليوت حقا بالنسبة لي --
and this should give you goose bumps:
وينبغي على هذا أن يدخلكم في مطبات ساذجة:
"we shall not cease from exploration
"علينا عدم الياس من الاستكشاف
and the end of our exploring shall be to return
ونهاية استكشافنا عليها أن تعود
where we started and know the place for the first time."
حيث بدأنا ومعرفة المكان من جديد"
And the next lines are, "Through the unknown remembered gate,
والأسطر التالية هي، "عبر البوابة الغير مستذكرة،
where the last of earth discovered
حيث اكتشف آخر الأرض
is that which is the beginning."
هي هذه الحقيقة"
So I have one message.
لذا لدي رسالة واحدة.
It seems to me that we’re all pointed in the wrong direction.
يبدو لي اننا جميعا موجهون الى الاتجاه الخاطئ.
For the rocketeers in the audience:
الى مطلقي الصواريخ في الجمهور،
I love what you’re doing, I admire the guts,
أنا أحب ما تفعلون، انا أعشق الشجاعة،
I admire the courage -- but your rockets
انا أعشق الاقدام، ولكن صواريخكم
are pointed in the wrong goddamn direction.
موجهة في الاتجاه الخاطئ الملعون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it’s all a question of perspective.
وهذا كله سؤال يعتمد على التصوّر.
Let me try and tell you --
دعوني أجرب وأقول لكم.
I don’t mean to insult you, but look,
أنا لا أقصد أن أهينكم، ولكن انظروا،
if I -- and I’m not doing this for real
اذا أنا -- وأنا لا أفعل هذا في الحقيقة
because it would be an insult,
لأنها ستكون اهانة،
so I’m going to pretend, and it softens the blow --
لذا سأقوم بالتظاهر، وستخفف من الصدمة.
I’m going to tell you what you’re thinking.
سأقول لكم ما الذي تفكرون به.
If I held up a square that was one foot square and the color of earth,
اذا حملت مربعاً و كانت مساحته قدم مربع، بلون الأرض،
and I held up another square that was the root two square --
وحملت مربعاً آخر وكان جذر الاثنين تربيع،
so it’s 1.5 times bigger -- and was the color of the oceans;
اذا انه أكبر ب مرة ونصف، وكان لون المحيط،
and I said, what is the relative value of these two things?
وقلت، ما هي القيمة النسبية لهذين الشيئين؟
Well, it’s the relative importance.
حسنا، انها الأهمية النسبية.
You would say -- yeah, yeah, yeah, we all know this;
سوف تقولون، نعم، نعم، نعم، جميعنا نعرف هذا.
water covers twice the area of the planet than dry land.
الماء يغطي ضعفي مساحة الكوكب من الأرض الجافة.
But it’s a question of perception,
لكن انها مسألة تصوّر.
and if that’s what you’re thinking,
واذا كان هذا ما تفكرون به،
if that’s what you think I mean when I say,
اذا كان هذا ما تفكرون به أقصد عندما أقول
"This is an ocean planet stupidly called 'Earth.'"
هذا كوكب محيط بغباء يسمى الأرض.
If you think that that’s the relative importance,
اذا كنتم تعتقدون انه هذه هي الأهمية النسبية،
two to one, you’re wrong by a factor of ten.
اثنان لواحد، فأنتم مخطئون بالنسبة لعشرة.
Now, you’re not as thick as two short planks,
الآن، أنتم لستم بسماكة لوحين من الخشب،
but you sound like it when you say "Earth,"
لكن تشبهون ذلك عندما تقولون "الأرض"،
because that demonstration, if I turned around this way --
لأن هذا الاثبات، اذا قلبته بهذه الطريقة،
that earth plane would be as thin as paper.
طبقة الأرض سوف تكون بنحف الورقة.
It’s a thin film, two-dimensional existence.
انه فيلم نحيف، وجود ببعدين.
The ocean representation would have a depth to it.
تمثيل المحيط سوف يكون له عمق .
And if you hefted those two things
واذا رفعتم هذين الشيئين
you might find that the relative scale of those is 20 to 1.
ربما تجدون المقياس المناسب لهم هو 20 لـ 1.
It turns out that something more than
يتبين أنه حوالي الأكثر من
94 percent of life on earth is aquatic.
94 بالمئة من الحياة على الأرض هو مائي.
That means that us terrestrials occupy a minority.
هذ يعني انه نحن الأرضيون نمثّل أقلية.
The problem we have in believing that
المشكلة التي لدينا هي في تصديق أنه
is -- you just have to give up this notion
عليك التخلي عن هذه الفكرة
that this Earth was created for us.
أن هذه الأرض خلقت لنا.
Because it’s a problem we have.
لأنها مشكلة لدينا.
If this is an ocean planet
اذا كان هذا كوكب محيط
and we only have a small minority of this planet,
ولدينا فقط أقلية صغيرة من هذا الكوكب،
it just interferes with a lot of what humanity thinks.
انه فقط يتعارض مع الكثير من ما تعتقده الانسانية.
Okay. Let me criticize this thing.
حسنا. دعوني أنتقد هذا الشيء.
I’m not talking about James Cameron --
أنا لا أتحدث عن جيمس كاميرون،
although I could, but I won’t.
مع أني أستطيع، ولكني لن أفعل.
You really do have to go and see his latest film,
عليكم حقا أن تذهبوا وتشاهدوا فيلمه الأخير،
"Aliens of the Deep." It’s incredible.
غرباء الأعماق. انه مذهل.
It features two of these deep rovers,
انه يلمّح لاثنين من هذه الغواصات الجوّالة،
and I can criticize them because these sweet things are mine.
وأنا أستطيع أن أنتقدهم لأن هذه الأشياء الحلوة هي ملكي.
This, I think, represents one of the most beautiful
هذا، باعتقادي، يعرض واحد من أجمل
classic submersibles built.
الغواصات الكلاسيكية المصنوعة.
If you look at that sub, you’ll see a sphere.
اذا نظرت للغواصة، سوف تجد جسم كروي.
This is an acryclic sphere.
هذا جسم كروي حلقي.
It generates all of the buoyancy,
هذا ينتج كل التعويم،
all of the payload for the craft,
كل الأحمال للمركب،
and the batteries are down here hanging underneath,
والبطاريات معلّقة هنا في الأسفل.
exactly like a balloon.
تماما مثل البالون.
This is the envelope, and this is the gondola, the payload.
هذا هو الغلاف وهذا هو الجندول، الحمولة.
Also coming up later for criticism are these massive lights.
أيضا يأتي لاحقا للنقد، هذه الأضواء الكبيرة.
And this one actually carries two great manipulators.
وهذا الشيء في الواقع يحمل مناورين هائلين.
It actually is a very good working sub --
انها في الواقع غواصة تعمل بشكل جيد جدا،
that’s what it was designed for.
هذا ما قد صممت لأجله.
The problem with it is --
المشكلة فيها هي،
and the reason I will never build another one like it --
والسبب الذي لن أبن واحدة مثلها،
is that this is a product of two-dimensional thinking.
أن هذا هو منتج من تفكير باتجاهين.
It’s what we humans do when we go in the ocean as engineers;
انه ما نفعله نحن البشر عندما نذهب للمحيط كمهندسين.
we take all our terrestrial hang-ups,
نأخذ كل معلّقاتنا البرية،
all our constraints -- importantly,
وكل قيودنا، والأهم،
these two-dimensional constraints that we have,
هذه القيود ثنائية البعد التي لدينا،
and they’re so constrained we don’t even understand it --
وهي مقيدة جدا لدرجة أننا لا نفهمها.
and we take them underwater.
ونأخذهم تحت الماء.
You notice that Jim Cameron is sitting in a seat.
لقد لاحظتم أن جيم كاميرون جالس في مقعد.
A seat works in a two-dimensional world,
مقعد يعمل في عالم ذي بعدين
where gravity blasts down on that seat, OK?
حيث الجاذبية تنفجر للأسفل على هذا المقعد، حسنا؟
And in a two-dimensional world,
و في عالم ذو بعدين،
we do know about the third dimension
نحن نعلم عن البعد الثالث
but we don’t use it because to go up
لكننا لا نستخدمه لأنه للصعود للأعلى
requires an awful lot of energy against gravity.
يتطلّب مقدار بشع من الطاقة ضد الجاذبية.
And then our mothers tell us,
و من ثم أمهاتنا تحكي لنا،
"Careful you don’t fall down" -- because you’ll fall over.
احذر أن تسقط للأسفل لأنك ستسقط على الأرض.
Now, go into the real atmosphere of this planet.
الآن، اذهب للجو الحقيقي لهذا الكوكب.
This planet has an inner atmosphere of water;
هذا الكوكب لديه جو داخلي من الماء.
it’s its inner atmosphere. It has two atmospheres --
انه جوّه الداخلي. لديه جوّان اثنان.
a lesser, outer gaseous atmosphere, a lighter one.
جو أقل، خارجي غازي ، جو خفيف.
Most of life on earth is in that inner atmosphere.
معظم الحياة على الأرض في هذا الجو.
And that life enjoys a three-dimensional existence,
وهذه الحياة تتمتع بوجود ثلاثي الأبعاد
which is alien to us.
وهو غريب علينا.
Fish do not sit in seats.
السمك لا يجلس على المقاعد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They don’t. Their mothers don’t say to little baby fish,
انهم لا يفعلون. أمهاتهم لا تقول لسمكة صغيرة،
"Careful you don’t fall over."
احذر أن تسقط.
They don’t fall over. They don’t fall.
انهم لا يسقطون للأسفل. انهم لا يسقطون.
They live in a three-dimensional world
انهم يعيشون في عالم ثلاثي الأبعاد
where there is no difference in energy
حيث هناك لا فرق في الطاقة
between going this way, that way, that way or that way.
بين الذهاب في هذا الاتجاه، ذاك الاتجاه، ذاك الاتجاه أو ذاك الاتجاه.
It’s truly a three-dimensional space.
انه فضاء ثلاثي الأبعاد حقا.
And we’re only just beginning to grasp it.
ونحن بدأنا نلحظه لتونا.
I don’t know of any other submersible,
أنا لا أعرف أي غاطسة أخرى،
or even remote, that just takes advantage
أو حتى بعيدة، فقط تأخذ الأفضلية
that this is a three-dimensional space.
أن هذا فضاء ثلاثي الأبعد.
This is the way we should be going into the oceans.
هذه الطريقة التي يجب أن نذهب بها الى المحيطات.
This is a three-dimensional machine.
هذه آلة ثلاثية الأبعاد.
What we need to do is go down into the ocean with the freedom of the animals,
ما علينا فعله هو الذهاب لأسفل المحيط بحرية الحيوانات،
and move in this three-dimensional space.
والحركة في هذا الفضاء ثلاثي الأبعاد.
OK, this is good stuff.
حسنا، هذا شيء جيد.
This is man’s first attempt at flying underwater.
هذه محاولة أولى للرجل للطيران تحت الماء.
Right now, I’m just coming down on this gorgeous, big, giant manta ray.
الآن، أنا سوف أنزل للأسفل لهذا المانتا راي العظيم، الكبير، الرائع.
She has twice the wingspan that I do.
لديها ضعفي امتداد الأجنحة التي لدي.
There I’m coming; she sees me.
هناك أنا آت، انها تراني.
And just notice how she rolls under and turns;
وفقط لاحظ كيف تدور للأسفل وتنعطف.
she doesn’t sit there and try and blow air into a tank
انها لا تجلس هناك و تحاول نفخ الهواء في خزان
and kind of flow up or sink down -- she just rolls.
و تطوف للأعلى أو تغطس للأسفل، انها فقط تدور.
And the craft that I’m in --
والحرفة التي أنا __
this hasn’t been shown before.
هذا لم يعرض من قبل.
Chris asked us to show stuff that hasn’t been shown before.
كريس سألنا أن نعرض مادة لم تعرض من قبل.
I wanted you to notice
أردتكم أن تلاحظوا
that she actually turned to come back up.
أنها في الواقع انعطفت للرجوع للأعلى.
There I am; I see her coming back,
ها هنا أنا؛ أراها تعود،
coming up underneath me.
تأتي للأعل تحتي.
I put reverse thrust and I try and pull gently down.
وضعت دفعة للخلف وحاولت وسحبت بهدوء للأسفل.
I’m trying to do everything very gently.
أنا أحاول فعل كل شيء بهدوء شديد.
We spent about three hours together and she’s beginning to trust me.
لقد قضينا ثلاث ساعات وقد بدأت تثق بي.
And this ballet is controlled by this lady here.
ورقصة الباليه هذه محكمة عن طريق هذه السيدة هنا.
She gets about that close and then she pulls away.
انها تقترب لهذه الدرجة ثم تنسحب بعيدا.
So now I try and go after her, but I’m practicing flying.
لذا أنا الآن أحاول وأذهب ورائها، لكن أنا أتدرب على الطيران.
This is the first flying machine. This was the first prototype.
هذه أول آلة طائرة. هذا كان أول نموذج.
This was a fly by wire. It has wings.
هذا كان طيران بالأسلاك. لديها أجنحة.
There’re no silly buoyancy tanks --
ليس هناك خزانات طفو سخيفة.
it’s permanently, positively buoyant.
انها دائمة، ايجابيا قابلة للطفو.
And then by moving through the water
و ثم عن طريق التحرّك عبر الماء
it’s able to take that control.
انها قادرة على ذلك التحكم.
Now, look at that; look, it’s -- she just blew me away.
الآن انظروا لهذا. يبدو أنه -- لقد غلبتني للتو.
She just rolled right away from underneath.
لقد دارت لليمين بعيدا من الأسفل،
Really that’s the only real dive I’ve ever made in this machine.
وحقيقة هذه الغطسة الحقيقية الوحيدة التي قمت بها في هذه الآلة.
It took 10 years to build.
لقد أستغرق تطويرها 10 سنوات.
But this lady here taught me, hah, taught me so much.
لكن السيدة هنا علمتني، هه، علمتني كثيرا.
We just learned so much in three hours in the water there.
لقد تعلمنا كثيرا خلال ثلاث ساعات فقط هناك في الماء.
I just had to go and build another machine.
لقد كان علي فقط أن أذهب و أبني آلة أخرى.
But look here. Instead of blowing tanks
لكن انظروا هنا. في مقابل تفجير الخزانات
and coming up slowly without thinking about it,
والصعود ببطء بدون التفكير به،
it’s a little bit of back pressure,
انه قليل من الضغط للوراء،
and that sub just comes straight back up out of the water.
وهذه الغواصة صعدت مباشرة للأعلى خارج الماء.
This is an internal Sony camera. Thank you, Sony.
هذه كاميرا سوني داخلية. شكرا لكم، سوني.
I don’t really look that ugly,
أنا لا أبدو هكذا بشع،
but the camera is so close that it’s just distorted.
لكن الكاميرا كانت جدا قريبة حتى أنني تشتت.
Now, there she goes, right overhead.
الآن، ها هي تذهب، مباشرة أعلى الرأس.
This is a wide-angle camera.
هذه كاميرا بزاوية منفرجة.
She’s just a few inches off the top of my head.
انها فقط على بعد انشات من سطح رأسي.
"Aah, ha, oh, he just crossed over the top of my head about,
"آه، ها، اوه، لقد مرّ مباشرة فوق سطح رأسي،
oh, I don’t know, just so close."
أوه، أنا لا أعرف، جدا قريب."
I come back up, not for air.
صعدت للأعلى، ليس للهواء.
"This is an incredible encounter with a manta. I’m speechless.
" هذا لقاء رائع مع مانتا. أنا لا أستطيع التحدّث.
We’ve been just feet apart. I’m going back down now."
لقد كنا على بعد أقدام. أنا ذاهب للأسفل الآن."
Okay, can we cut that? Lights back up please.
حسانا، هل بامكاننا قطع هذا؟ الأضواء مجددا لو سمحتم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Trying to fly and keep up with that animal --
محاولة الطيران والمواصلة مع هذا الحيوان،
it wasn’t the lack of maneuverability that we had.
انها لم تكن قلّة القدرة على المناورة التي لدينا،
It was the fact she was going so slow.
لقد كان الواقع أنها كانت تسير ببطء شديد.
I actually designed that to move faster through the water
أنا في الواقع صممت هذا للحركة أسرع في الماء.
because I thought that was the thing
لأني اعتقدت أنها كانت الشيء
that we needed to do: to move fast and get range.
الذي علينا فعله: الحركة أسرع والحصول على النطاق.
But after that encounter I really did want to go back with that animal and dance.
لكن بعد هذا اللقاء أردت فعلا العودة مع هذا الحيوان والرقص.
She wanted to dance.
لقد أرادت أن ترقص.
And so what we needed to do was increase the wing area
ولهذا ما كان علينا فعله هو زيادة مساحة الجناح
so that we just had more grip, develop higher forces.
لذا كان لدينا قبض أكثر، تطوير قوى أعلى.
So the sub that was outside last year -- this is the one.
اذا الغواصة التي أطلقت السنة الماضية، هذه هي.
You see the larger wing area here.
أنت ترون المساحة الأكبر للجناح هنا.
Also, clearly, it was such a powerful thing,
أيضا، بوضوح، لكن كان شيئا قويا،
we wanted to try and bring other people
لقد أردنا أن نجرّب ونحضر مزيدا من الناس
but we couldn't figure out how to do it.
و كان باستطاعتنا معرفة كيف نفعلها.
So we opened the world’s first flight school.
لذا فتحنا أول مدرسة طيران في العالم.
The rational for the world’s first flight school
منطق أول مدرسة طيران في العالم
goes something like: when the coastguards come up to me and say --
ينص على الآتي، عندما يأتي حرس الشاطئ الي ويقولون--
they used to leave us alone when we were diving
لقد اعتادوا على تركنا لوحدنا عندما كنا نغطس
these goofy little spherical things,
بهذه الأشياء الكروية البلهاء الصغيرة.
but when we started flying around
لكن عندما بدأنا بالطيران
in underwater jet fighters they got a little nervous --
بمقاتلات تحت الماء أصبحوا غاضبين.
they would come up and say,
ويريدون أن يأتوا ويقولوا،
"Do you have a license for that?"
هل لديكم رخصة لهذا؟
And then I’d put my sunglasses on, the beard
ثم أضع نظاراتي الشمسية على اللحية
that would all sprout out, and I would say,
التي تنمو بسرعة، وأقول،
"I don’t need no stinking license."
أنا لست بحاجة لرخصة كريهة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"I write these stinking license," which I do.
أنا أكتب هذه الرخص الكريهة، التي أفعلها.
So Bob Gelfond's around here --
لذا بوب جيلفونز * حول هنا--
but somebody in the audience here has license number 20.
لكن أحدا ما في الحضور لديه الرخصة رقم 20.
They’re one of the first subsea aviators.
انهم واحد من أول الطيارين تحت الماء.
So we’ve run two flight schools.
اذا نحن ندير مدرستين للطيران.
Where the hell that goes, I don’t know, but it’s a lot of fun.
اين ذهب هذا بحق الجحيم، أنا لا أعرف، لكنه مسلي كثيرا.
What comes next in 30 seconds? I can’t tell you.
ماذا ياتي لاحقا خلال 30 ثانية؟ لا أستطيع أن أقول لكم.
But the patent for underwater flight --
لكن براءة اختراع الطيران تحت الماء،
Karen and I, we were looking at it,
كارين و أنا، كنا نتطلع لها.
some business partners wanted us to patent it --
بعض شركاء العمل أرادوا منا أنا نعملها براءة اختراع.
we weren’t sure about that.
لكننا لم نكن متأكدين من ذلك.
We’ve decided we’re just going to let that go.
لقد قررنا أن ننسى الموضوع.
It just seems wrong to try and patent --
انه يبدو خطأ أن تجرّب و تعمل براءة اختراع --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
-- the freedom for underwater flight.
-- الحرية للطيران تحت الماء.
So anybody who wants to copy us
لذا أي أحد يريد النسخ منا
and come and join us, go for it.
والمجيء والنضمام الينا، بكل إريحية.
The other thing is that we’ve got much lower costs.
الشيء الآخر هو أنه لدينا كلفة أقل بكثير.
We developed some other technology
لقد طوّرنا تكنولوجيا أخرى
called spider optics, and Craig Ventner asked me
تسمى عنكبوت البصريات، و كريغ فينتنير سألني
to make an announcement here this morning:
أن أعمل اعلانا هنا هذا الصباح.
we’re going to be building a beautiful, little,
سوف نقوم ببناء نسخة جميلة، صغيرة،
small version of this -- unmanned, super deep --
من هذا، غير مزوّد بالرجال، عميق جدا،
for his boat to go and get back some deep sea DNA stuff.
لقاربه للذهاب وأخذ بعض أشياء ال دي أن أي للبحر العميق.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.